Paul Druce

Last updated: 3rd June 2024

Current responsibilities

Senior Software Engineer in Test, The MathWorks

May 2023 - Current

I work with multiple teams to implement comprehensive CI pipelines and help design software to make it testable, scalable and cloud ready.

Skills learnt:

- Kubernetes based web app development.
- Deployment of modern web app on Azure and AWS.
- Managing software release pipelines.
- Golang development and testing.
- Refactoring existing codebases to align with best practices

Software Engineer in Test, The MathWorks

May 2022 - May 2023

As part of the Cloud Platform Integrations team at MathWorks, I worked on integrating MATLAB in Jupyter notebooks. Also worked on Modelscape - a new offering from The MathWorks aimed at helping financial institutions manage their models.

Skills learnt:

- JavaScript and TypeScript development and testing.
- Python development and testing.
- Build and test pipelines in TeamCity and GitHub Actions
- Docker for environment reproducibility and testing.
- Automated GUI testing using Playwright framework.

Skills

- Experienced in high performance computing and commercial software in C and C++.
- Fluent in the following programming languages: C, C++, JavaScript/TypeScript, Golang, Python and Bash
- Experienced using Git and Perforce for collaborative development.
- Experienced setting up CI pipelines using GitHub Actions and TeamCity.
- Experience using Linux, macOS and Windows development environments.
- Internet of Things development using ESP8266/ESP32 and other devices, i.e., Arduino framework, ESP-DF framework, micropython as well as how to use PlatformIO.
- Experience in data analysis using Python and Mathematica.
- Experienced using LaTex (including TikZ and beamer) and the Microsoft Office suite.
- Web development, including animations; $\operatorname{HTML/CSS/JavaScript}.$

Previous Professional Experience

Consulting Engineering at MachineWorks

May 2021 - April 2022

I aided commercial 3D software developers to implement and use MachineWorks software for a wide variety of applications, using the languages C, C++ and C#.

I also create demonstrative applications to show case MachineWorks software in new markets.

This includes the creation of new workflows and GUI applications.

I also develop algorithms and create example code for customers to use in their products to facilitate their products to market faster.

Academic Tutor and Mentor

Aug 2017 - May 2023

I am an experienced tutor in mathematics and physics at the levels of university, A level and GCSE.

I also mentored students for various mathematical entrance exams and the UKMT mathematical competitions.

I have vast experience in both face-to-face tutoring and online tutoring via shared online whiteboards. I prepared lessons and question sheets at appropriate levels for my tutees. My role was to build the confidence and the abilities of my students and provide them with a comfortable environment to ask any questions they may have.

Education

PhD in Mathematical Sciences, University of Nottingham, UK:

2015 - 2020

Title: Spectral Geometry of Fuzzy Spaces

Supervisor: Prof. John Barrett

I developed the understanding of finite non-commutative geometries and how they might be useful in the theory of quantum gravity.

Mathematical areas studied: Differential geometry, non-commutative geometry, quantum geometry, representation theory.

Key skills developed: independent working, public speaking, data analysis using Python, knowledge of Monte Carlo simulations

For my PhD I worked on an area of mathematics called non-commutative geometry and how it might be useful in the theory of quantum gravity. My research was to investigate the use of called *fuzzy spaces* as candidates for quantum spacetimes. I investigated the dimension and volume of these spaces by analysing the spectrum of the Dirac operator. I also investigated the role of Lie group symmetries in restricting the fuzzy spaces possible.

In pursuit of my research I developed my knowledge of data analysis using the language Python. I also became familiar with the workings of Monte Carlo simulations and the application of machine learning to physical problems. A topic I am very interested in pursuing further.

First Class Masters in Mathematics and Physics, University of Warwick, UK:

Masters Dissertation: Multiferroicity Emerging from Frustrated Spin Interactions

Supervisors: Prof J. Staunton and Dr J. Lloyd-Hughes

Year 1: 69.3%, Year 2: 82.8%, Year 3: 82.9%, Year 4: 83.0%, Overall grade: 81.6%

During my time at Warwick, I studied a wide range of mathematics and physics topics. My interests were in both the abstract mathematics and the physics of matter and its constituents. Here is a list of topics I studied during my time at Warwick: Real Analysis, Differential Equations, Groups and Rings, Complex Analysis, Classical Mechanics, Statistical Physics, General Relativity, Solid State Physics, Fluid Dynamics and many more. I maintained an average grade of 81% throughout my course achieving one of the best marks in the year. I became proficient in the programming language C and its use in high-performance computing. I learnt how to implement parallel computing by making us of OpenMP and MPI frameworks.

A Levels, King Edward Vi Sixth Form, Sheffield, UK:

2009 - 2011

Maths: A*, Physics: A, Chemistry: A.

GCSEs, Birley Community College, Sheffield, UK:

2004 - 2009

9 A's, 2 B's and one C.

Teaching Experience

• UKMT Volunteer Mentor

October 2020 - May 2022

I was a volunteer for the UK Mathematics Trust. My role involved mentoring the students who are entering the advanced UKMT competitive mathematics exams. I was also involved in various outreach projects that the UKMT organise. I aided with the creation of appropriate questions and aided in the distribution of content via social media.

PhD Demonstrating and Marking

Oct 2015 - Jul 2019

Alongside my PhD, I was employed to help students with their questions for various undergraduate mathematics modules for Engineering students, Physics students and Mathematics students. This includes courses such as Introduction to Mathematical Physics (2nd year), Differential Equations and Fourier Analysis (2nd year), Applied Mathematics (1st year) and more. I also mark the mid-term exams and coursework for various modules.

Introduction to Mathematical Physics (2nd year)
 Mathematics for Physics and Astronomy (1st year)
 Calculus and Linear Algebra (1st year for Natural Science students)
 Applied Mathematics (1st year)
 Mathematical Analysis (2nd year)
 Differential Equations and Fourier Analysis (2nd year)
 Spring 2016

Spring 2016

Non-commutative Geometry Seminar Series for Master Students Oct 2016 - Apr 2017

I organised and delivered a seminar on topics surrounding my research over the course of two semesters. The seminar was delivered to masters students at the University of Nottingham. The was regularly attended by around 10 students despite it not being for credit towards their degree. The course resulted in two students choosing noncommutative geometry as the subject for their masters dissertation, and one of the students chose to undertake a PhD with my supervisor. Some lecture notes suitable for a UK masters student were developed on the foundational results of non-commutative geometry.

• Undergraduate Revision Classes

2012-2015

As part of the Warwick Physics Society:

- I updated and maintained revision guides
- I organised and ran revision lectures on various topics
- I provided workshops to run alongside a university course. These were aimed at first time programmers in C programming, to help them understand the language and develop the programming skills necessary.

Academic Activities

Research Interests

My research interests span a wide area within Mathematical Physics. I am deeply interested in the mathematical description of the universe with emphasis on the precise nature of spacetime. With my recent work investigating the use of noncommutative geometry to model spacetimes with a high energy cutoff. I also interested in any novel use of mathematics in physical situations, such as the use of topology and algebraic methods in condensed matter studies.

Outreach

I am an enthusiastic advocate for mathematics and science. I was on the organisational committee for the international festival Pint of Science 2019. I helped organise the Nottingham branch where academics from the University of Nottingham go to the pubs of Nottingham to explain their current research to the public in an understandable manner. I am always looking for ways to bring mathematics and science out of the universities and into public view.

Past Research Projects

PhD Research Project - Spectral Geometry of Fuzzy Spaces

2015-2019

Keywords: Noncommutative geometry, Monte Carlo simulations, spectral geometry, quantum gravity, symmetries in physics

My PhD research was concerned with the use of finite noncommutative geometries as candidates for quantum spacetimes. These so-called *fuzzy spaces* possess an energy cutoff whilst retaining Lie group symmetries. My PhD research was to investigate the dimension and volume of these spaces by analysing the spectrum of the Dirac operator. I also investigated the role of Lie group symmetries in restricting the possible fuzzy spaces possible.

Masters Research Project - Multiferroicity Emerging from Frustrated Spin Interactions 2014-2015

Keywords: Solid-state physics, Theoretical physics, mathematical modelling, frustrated systems, quantum mechanics.

During the Masters' year of my undergraduate degree, I undertook a research project, supervised by Prof. J. Staunton and Dr. J. Lloyd-Hughes, in which we investigated the various spin configurations of materials with a multiferroic phase. We aimed to identify what was special about these materials spin configurations that caused them to possess a multiferroic phase. This project was conducted with the aim of aiding the design of high temperature multiferroic devices. We specifically studied Cupric Oxide (CuO) which has a multiferroic phase between 213K and 230K, primarily by using mean field model. This project resulted in a functional model which predicted a multiferroic phase at a temperature which is in reasonable agreement with the experimental values.

Undergraduate Summer Research - Knotted Nematics August 2014-September 2014

Keywords: Condensed Matter, Mathematical Physics, Liquid Crystals, statistical physics

This was funded under the Undergraduate Research Scholarship Scheme and was supervised under G. P. Alexander at The University of Warwick. The main aim of this research was to develop a construction for describing knotted liquid crystals, specifically knotted nematics. We improved upon existing ideas that used Milnor's Fibration Theorem and developed a method to construct the necessary complex polynomial for Milnor's theorem, for a given knot.

Publications

Spectral estimators for finite non-commutative geometries. Barrett, J., Druce, P., Glaser, L.: J Phys Math Theor. 52, 275203 (2019). doi:10.1088/1751-8121/ab22f8

Grants and Awards

- Non-commutative Geometry and Quantum Gravity EPSRC Studentship, funding my PhD studies, hosted by the University of Nottingham (September 2015 September 2018)
- Knotted Nematics funded as an Undergraduate Research Scholarship Scheme by the University of Warwick, and supervised by Dr G. P. Alexander (August-September 2014).

Talks

- Noncommutative Geometry and Gravity Models Talk given at Collabor8.2 meeting at Lancaster University, UK, May 2018. Slides here.
- Fuzzy Geometries and Spectral Zeta Functions. Invited by Lisa Glaser at Radboud University, Netherlands, April 2017. Slides here.
- Algebraic Knots and Liquid Crystals. At the Warwick Imperial Autumn Meeting, 2014 (University of Warwick, UK, November 2014). Slides here.
- Poster presented at Quantum Gravity on the Computer conference March 2018. PDF here.

Conferences Attended

- Gauge Theories and Noncommutative Geometry Nijmegen, April 2016, http://www.noncommutativegeometry.nl/ncg2016/
- Quantum Structure of Spacetime Belgrade, August 2016, http://qssg16.ipb.ac.rs/
- Quantum Spacetime Porto, January 2017, https://www.fc.up.pt/quantumspacetime17/
- Talking Maths in Public Bath, September 2017, http://talkingmathsinpublic.uk/
- Quantum Spacetime and Physics Models Corfu, September 2017, http://www.physics.ntua.gr/corfu2017/qg.html
- Quantum Structure of Spacetime Sofia, February 2018, http://theo2.inrne.bas.bg/~dobrev/ QST-18.htm
- Quantum Gravity on the Computer Stockholm, March 2018, https://agenda.albanova.se/conferenceDisplay.py?confId=6242
- Collabor8.2 Lancaster, May 2018, http://www.collabor8research.com/
- Physical Applications of Fuzzy Spaces Brussels, January 2019

Other professional experiences

• Open Day Assistant at the University of Warwick

September 2012 - July 2015

Throughout my undergraduate degree I was part of the open day team for the Physics department at Warwick university. My role included taking the prospective students on tours of the campus, informing them of important and interesting aspects of the university. I was also given the responsibility to present experiments to prospective students, engaging them with thought provoking questions. I was also part of the team to inform the prospective students about the courses available by the Physics department and answer any questions they may have about life at university.

• Administrative Worker at Split The Bills Ltd.

Aug-September 2012

My roles in this temporary role was to communicate with the student registering for the service and then contact utility providers to setup the new accounts. Handling any issues that would arise in a timely and professional manner.

• Warehouse Operative at River Island

2010-2011

I was part of the team that unpackaged new deliveries of clothes and prepare clothing to be presented on the store floor. This required adaptability as each delivery changed in size. As well as good team work and communication as the unpacking procedure was split in to various stages, with a separate person per stage. As well as working in an efficient manner. I was also responsible for searching and retrieving clothing requested by the store front.

• Voluntary Sale Assistant at British Heart Foundation

2010-2011

My role at the British Heart Foundation included assisting customers in finding items, informing them about the charity and maintaining the store. As the British Heart Foundation has a wide range of customers and staff, I had to quickly learn to adapt my communication and sales approach to fit their needs and situation.